now let's talk about a browser scenario
where uh we have got multiple tabs and
we need to move between this tabs uh for
our different scenarios right so if I've
got four five different tabs on this
stenters vehicle insurance I want to
switch between different tabs maybe I
want to go to the third tab or the fifth
Tab and again I want to go back to the
third and the first tab so this is the
scenario
and now the question is um how can we do
this so there is no direct way of uh
switching uh the tabs there is no method
in tosa which you can use to basically
switch between different tabs right but
whenever you don't find any direct
method you can always fall back upon um
how the user is basically uh doing this
uh maybe from the keyboard or from the
mouse and then you can emulate those
actions uh from tosa now we know that we
can emulate any particular action which
we perform from the keyboard uh in tosa
uh so uh in this particular scenario uh
if we want to switch to a particular
browser tab we can always use uh the tab
option right so uh when you press
control+ tab it is going to switch
between different tabs like I'm doing
right now and if I want to switch back
to a previous tab I can also use control
shift and tab okay so these are the
keyboard
shortcuts which can be used in scenarios
where you don't have any other option
like a direct method so you can
basically send these keys from tosa and
then you can um achieve what you want to
do with your particular automation right
so uh let's try and now uh replicate
this in our test cases so let me quickly
create a new folder I'm going to call
this
browser and here we will create a new
test case called switch
tabs okay here um I'm going to add a
test step uh which is the tbox send
keys and here uh we need to pass a
caption and a key so caption uh it is we
know the brows the title here so it T
Trend this vehicle insurance throughout
right so what I can do is I can use a
part of the text here and then I can put
a regular expression so I will use that
t and this part here
okay and now in the keys uh what I can
do is I can pass the control key and in
this case we can pass the carot sign uh
so it implies the control and then we
can pass the browser tab number okay so
if you know where which browser tab you
want to switch to you can directly pass
the number here so if I want to switch
to the third tab I can pass control+ 3
okay now um if I go ahead and run
this okay so we were already on the
third tab so it will not make any
difference so uh let me go ahead and
switch back to the first tab now okay
and let's go ahead and done this
again okay so now you see that uh it
switched to the third tab now in in
cases where I don't know which
particular tab is the next tab uh what
is the number for that okay um so if I
want to switch to the next tab but I
don't know the number of tabs then um I
can always use the control+ tab key
right so what I will do I will just copy
this and
here instead of the number uh we will
pass
control and then we will pass
tab okay so it will now uh switch to the
next tab so let's go ahead and run this
now okay so as you can see uh it
switched to the fourth tab
right now uh similarly if I want to
switch to the previous tab okay uh
without passing the number so again uh
we can use a shortcut here so let's do
that what we will do here is uh we will
pass Control Plus shift plus tab okay
and the shortcut for that is the plus
sign so the plus sign implies the shift
the Scot sign implies the control and
this is the tab so in total it is contr
plus shift plus tab now if I run
this okay you will see it will move on
to the third
tab now if you're not sure about what
are the shortcut for all the different
Keys you can always go to the Microsoft
send Keys page okay so there is a send
Keys class uh which you can search for
uh in Microsoft and that will actually
give you all the different uh keys or
the code for all the keyboard Keys uh
which you want to use okay so these are
all the code you can see here and these
are the exact codes which we can use uh
in tosa as well okay so we used the tab
here you can see and then if I go a
little bit down then you will see the
code for shift it is plus for control uh
it is this uh carot sign and and then
for all it is percentage okay so these
are all the codes uh which can be used
uh for the different keyboard keys and
you can always use them in scenarios
where you don't have a direct V of
automation using the default tosa
modules then just use the keyboard keys
and do the other way around like a
normal user would do so just emulate
that particular action using the send
Keys module